Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1880-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
- Photographic views of Sherman's Campaign, embracing scenes of the occupation of Nashville, the great battles around Chattanooga and Lookout Mountain, the Campaign of Atlanta, March to the Sea, and the Great Raid through the Carolinas / From negatives taken in the field, by Geo. N. Barnard, Officia
  Includes accompanying pamphlet with descriptions of the images; Sherman and his generals; the "Capitol," Nashville, Tenn.; Nashville from the Capitol; Trestle bridge at Whiteside; Pass in the Raccoon Range, No. 1; Pass in the Raccoon Range, No. 2; Chattanooga, from the North; Mission ridge, from Orchard Knob; Orchard Knob, from Mission Ridge; The crest of Mission Ridge; Mission Ridge, scene of Sherman's attack; Chattanooga Valley, from Lookout Mountain (2 views); LuLa Lake, Lookout Mountain; The John Ross House; Ringold, Ga.; Buzzards' Roost; the Battle Ground of Resaca, No. 1; No. 2; No. 3; Resaca, from the rebel works; Defenses of the Etawah Bridge; Allatoona Pass, from the Etawah; Battlefield of New Hope church, Ga., No. 1; No. 2; the "Hell Hole," Battlefield of New Hope church; The Allatoona Pass; the Allatoona Pass, looking North; Pine Mountain; Our Line in front of Kenesaw Mountain; View from Kenesaw Mountain; South Bank of the Chattahoochie; The battlefield of Peach Tree Creek; Scenes of Gen. McPherson's Death; Battlefield of Atlanta, 22d July, 1864, No. 1; No.2; the Potter House, Atlanta; Rebel Works in front of Atlanta, No.3; No. 4; Destruction of Hood's ordnance train; view of Atlanta, Ga., No. 1; No. 2; Savannah River, near the city; Buen Ventura, Savannah; Savannah, looking up the river; Savannah, looking down the river; Fountain, and park, Savannah; The New Capitol, Columbia, S.C.; Ruins in Columbia, S.C. (2 views); Fort Sumter; Interior view of Fort Sumter; Exterior view of Fort Sumter; ruins of the Pinckney Mansion, Charleston; Ruins in Charleston, S.C.; Ruins of the R.R. Depot, Charleston.
- [Richard C. Patterson, Jr., (1886-1966) albums], 1947-1949; 13613 (Volume 396.1)
  Small brown album: including views of formal dinners and luncheons, Regional Industrial Conference; guests at a New Year's dinner; giving a speech; members of the "Pelican' club, 1948 at Bohemian Grove, Calif.; pictured with Thomas J. Watson; views in Guatemala, including Patterson presenting his credentials, views of the embassy, on official visits, meeting with Emergency Flood Committee, with family, at a conference of American Ambassadors from the Caribbean area in Cuba.
- [Richard C. Patterson, Jr., (1886-1966) albums], [1890]-1945; 13612 (Volume 396.2)
  Large brown album: early photographs of Patterson with family, and as a child; views in Italy with Clare Booth Luce, 1945; in China, 1921, showing gardens, visiting a dye plant; at luncheon, in Rickshaw; at a mine; as Prison Commissioner, with Prison band and WOR radio microphone, outside Jefferson Market Prison, with Mayor Walker, Armistice Day ceremonies; Mary Pickford addressing inmates at the Workhouse; as executive vice-president of N.B.C., with Mayor LaGuardia and others at N.B.C. studios; at opening of Radio City; at dinners and luncheons; as Assistant Secretary of Commerce; at Monopoly Committee meeting; with Eleanor Roosevelt; with Ginger Rogers; at premiere of Citizen Kane; with Gloria Swanson at luncheon for Cecil B. de Mille; at fingerprinting of RKO employees; as ambassador to Yugoslavia, being briefed on activities on the Italian front; at Vatican after meeting with Pope Pius; with Marshall Tito; with wedding party in tradition costume; on a hunting trip.
- [Richard C. Patterson, Jr., (1886-1966) albums], 1949-1954; 13611 (Volume 396.3)
  "Photos No. 4": views in Guatemala; at various luncheons and dinners, in Calif., N.C.; as Ambassador to Switzerland, 1951, views of the ambassadors residence, including interiors; golfing in Cran; William Tell Memorial; at Inauguration of Mayor Robert Wagner; as part of the Mayor's Reception Committee; with Sir Edmund Hillary; at board of director's meetings, and charity functions; with Pres. Truman at dinner in honor of his 70th birthday; with Haille Selassie.
- [Richard C. Patterson, Jr., (1886-1966) albums], 1954-1958; 13610 (Volume 396.4)
  "Photos #5": at luncheons and other official events; with Prmie ministers, ambassadors, Kings, and with the Queen Mother atop the Empire State building, the Shah of Iran and Queen Soraya, with Eleanor Roosevelt on Human Rights Day; visiting Rome; visiting uranium mine in Colorado; at receptions at the Metropolitan, and at the U.N.; on the Aerotrain at Penn Station; greeting dignitaries at the Heliport; rededication of City Hall; Patterson donkeys; Queen Elizabeth and Prince Phillip at Stapleton, Staten Island, 1957.
- [Richard C. Patterson, Jr., (1886-1966) albums], 1919-1964; 13609 (Volume 396.5)
  "Photos #7": as part of the American Peace Comm., 1919; in China, 1920s; some photos repeating events shown in earlier albums; efforts to sell War Bonds; then album picks up from where "Photos #5" left off; opera performance at Bohemia Grove, Calif.; S.S. Nautilus Parade, 1958; Fidel Casto receiving replica of Empire State Bldg., 1959; Hudson River celebration, Rockefeller, Nixon, et al., Consular Corps Jones Beach parties; visiting Japan, visiting Iran; with Bob Hope at March of Dimes dinner; ticker tape parade for John Glenn; City Hall Ceremony honoring the NY Mets, 1962, welcoming team to city; Pres. John Kennedy to officiate at groundstone laying ceremony for U.S. Pavilion at World's Fair; with Vice Pres. Johnson at funeral of Pope John, 1963.
- [Richard C. Patterson, Jr., (1886-1966) albums], 1964-1965; 13608 (Volume 396.6)
  "R.C.P., Jr., Photos": as chief of protocol, with dignitaries at World's Fair, including King Hussein; receiving awards; at reception for Martin Luther King, Jr. at ceremonies at Gracie Mansion, at Explorers Club dinner in honor of Lowell Thomas. Folder of extra prints supplementing those in the albums. See also Album #62.
- Volume 397, 13606
  Mr. Vanderbilt's house and collections / described by Edward Strahan [pseud.], has been separated from the Album File and made its own Collection, now PR-169.
- Old Times in the Bronx; A collection of photographs 1883-1904, with a guide by Howard Masten Canoune. New York: 1926., 13605 (Volume 398)
  Old Tremont, 1883-1903; Old Mount Hope, 1884-1904; Echo Park and Burnside Avenue, 1891-1899; Claremont Park and Mount Eden, 1892-1904; Brown's Woods, 1890; Washington Bridge and High Bridge, 1890-1891; New York University and the Hall of Fame, 1893; Madison Avenue and Forty First Street, Bethesda Fountain and the Ramble in Central Park, 1891; Crotona Park and the Indian Lake, 1891; The Bronx River from West Farms to Lorillard's, 1891-1893; views along the Bronx River are an area now in the New York Botanical Garden.
- Canoune Family Yesteryears, AD 1892-1904, 13603 (Volume 399)
  Views in Mt. Hope, N.Y., of the children of Mr. and Mrs. Alonzo G. Cannon, their pets, and others; at Avon and Allaire, N.J.; Canoune family members, Howard Masten Canoune's diplomas and passport; views at Macon Street, Brooklyn; family cats Dewey and Malta; snow storm, Jan. 1904; views in Orange County.
- Canoune Family Yesteryears, AD 1905-1916, 13601 (Volume 400)
  Views in Avon and Plainfield N.J. of family, including Mrs. H. M. Canoune and children; views from trips to California, Italy.
- Canoune Family Yesteryears, Vol. V - 1921-1929, 13599 (Volume 401)
  Family photographs at Plainfield, Princeton, N.J. and Long Island, N.Y., including sailing and beach views; the family dogs including views at a dog show; a trip to Washington, D.C. and Arlington, Va.
- Canoune Family Yesteryears, Vol. VI - 1926, European Tour, 13597 (Volume 402)
  France and England, including snapshots, postcards and souvenirs.
- Canoune Family Yesteryears, AD 1917-1920, 13595 (Volume 403)
  Views of the family at home, and on outings to the Catskills and Long Island, including beach scenes.
- Metropolitan Hospital, Department of Hospitals, City of New York. On Welfare Island (Old Blackwell's Island) in East River (1894-1937). Wards Island (1875-1894) was its predecessor. / Arranged in this album, August 1937. Property of Frederick M. Dearborn., 1875-1937; 13593 (Volume 404)
  228 illustrations covering period from October 1875 to February 1937; views of hospitals, including interiors and staff.
- Ex Libris Bessie White [Album of photographs of a ball, possibly held by Mr. & Mrs. Charles Tracy Barney], undated; 13591 (Volume 405)
  Bessie White bookplate; Including photographs of Helen and Katherine Barney, Mr. And Mrs. Stanford White, and others, all in Elizabethan costume. Two group portraits showing guests seated at long tables in a room with large ornate mantle, exposed and painted beams, and hung with tapestries.
- [Album of photographs made during the expedition of the American Asiatic fleet into Korea, May and June, 1871], 13589 (Volume 406)
  Views of Korean officials, officers aboard various vessels, marines at battlefields, Korean casualties, views of the Salee River and the American ships; lacquer cover.
- Beekman House, 35 East 38th Street, New York, 1910, 13587 (Volume 407)
  Interior views; platinum prints.
- New York City, North River from the Jersey City side, [1880]; 13585 (Volume 408)
  Panoramic view of the piers along the North (Hudson) River, and the New York skyline beyond, with the spires of churches rising above other buildings; Brooklyn Bridge under construction; Brooklyn waterfront; images mounted on board with letterpress captions identifying landmarks.
- New York City, North River from the Jersey City side, [1880]; 13583 (Volume 409)
  Panoramic view of the piers along the North (Hudson) River, and the New York skyline beyond, with the spires of churches rising above other buildings; Brooklyn Bridge under construction; Brooklyn waterfront.
- Grand Central Terminal Improvement, 1910; 13581 (Volume 410)
  Copies of renderings showing the new Grand Central station, including the 42nd and 45th Street elevations, the Post Office at Lexington Ave. and 43rd Street; Substation No. 1 of the New York Central and Hudson River Railroad Co., at 50th Street Between Lexington and Park; railyard designs, including suburban level, dated 1905; the express level; street level showing layout of streets above tracks; plan labeled "Office" showing the next level up; Longitudinal section on Park Ave., 42nd Street elevation, showing layout of tunnels, Section through Concourse, Section through Train Room; Section through 46th Street looking north, section south of 52nd Street looking north, section through 55th Street looking north, Section through 57th Street; section on cross section of 44th Street, looking north; longitudinal sections on Park Avenue.
- Douglas L. Elliman & Co.: New York Central Transformation, 1906-1930; 13579 (Volume 411)
  Photographs and drawings depicting the area north of Grand Central Station, including the yards all above ground, and their gradual lowering to below grade; includes views of Park Avenue when first completed and general views of the area showing construction and transformation of the neighborhood.
- [Hummer album], [1870-1900]; 13577 (Volume 412)
  Cartes-de-visite, cabinet cards and tintypes of unidentified men, women and children by photographers from New York, New Jersey and Stroudsburg, PA, including a view of two men outside a shop with a sign reading J. Hummer Boot and Shoe Maker.
- [Schermerhorn clippings album], undated; 13575 (Volume 413)
  Clippings of reproductions depicting historic sites, clippings showing buildings, churches, etc. in Manhattan; family photographs laid in, including home at 66 W. 37th and 74 W. 68th; interior views including family seated at table with servant standing by; boy on donkey; churches.
- [Albums of photographs in New York and vicinity], 1902-[1910]; 13573 (Volume 414)
  Amateur photographs; Luna Park at night, and other Coney Island views, including the beach; views in Central Park, Bronx Park and Prospect Park, including bridges, snow scenes and skating, the entrance at Grand Army plaza, including the arch, summer houses, waterfalls, "Mr. Clark" and a boy and a girl; sleighing party in Prospect Park, 1902; Grant's tomb; City Hall and Brooklyn borough hall decorated in bunting, May 1903; cattle and ducks in pasture, Staten Island; ship on the East River; William's Bridge and speedway; Bronx park, including river and mill, Art Museum; rivers at Patterson, N.J., and Glen Falls; water tower in Prospect Park, Cleopatra's Needle; sculpture: Washington at the Customs House, Beecher in Brooklyn; Fort Greene Park; Police parade; Fort William, Governor's Island; "Carrie at House, 1903" and Allie in Prospect Park (in sailor suit); group of men with St. Bernard in Central Park; family group on roof; warships at the Brooklyn Navy Yard.
- The House of Bishops of the Protestant Episcopal Church of the United States/photographed from life during the triennial convention by J. Gurney & son., 1862; 13571 (Volume 415)
  Published by T. Porter Shaw, New York. 24 leaves of plates. Album contains portraits of Episcopal Bishops, with names and biographies on facing pages. Bishops shown are: Thomas Church Brownell, John Henry Hopkins, Benjamin Bosworth Smith, Charles Pettit McIlvaine, Jackson Kemper, Samuel Allen McCoskry, William Heathcote de Lancey, Alfred Lee, Manton Eastburn, Carlton Chase, Cicero Stephens Hawks, Alonzo Potter, George Burgess, George Upfold (portrait missing), John Williams, Henry John Whitehouse (portrait missing), Henry Washington Lee, Horatio Potter, Thomas March Clark, William Henry Odenheimer, Greg. Thurston Bedell (portrait missing), Henry Benjamin Whipple, Joseph Cruickshank Talbot, William Bacon Stevens.
- [Snapshots of the 1939 World's Fair], 1939, Jul.; 13569 (Volume 416)
  Photographs by William Huf. 14 3.5 x 5" photos of the 1939 World's Fair in New York show the Trylon and Perisphere from many angles; a children's parade with a band and elephants; the Communications Building and the AT & T Building.
- [Snapshots of the 1939 World's Fair], 1939, Jul.; 13567 (Volume 417)
  Photographs by William Huf. 12 3.5 x 5" photos of the 1939 World's Fair in New York show the country pavilions. Japan, U.S.S.R., Italy, France, the United States, and Britain's buildings are shown, as well as the Court of Peace and its fountain.
- [Camp Easton for Boys, Sharon, Conn.], 1952-1956; 13565 (Volume 418)
  Unbound album with black pages, black and white photos (some 8x10, some smaller) pasted in. Some captions in white. Group photographs of campers and counselors, action shots of male campers playing sports, eating, painting, swimming, and hiking.
- [Scenes of England], ca. 1871; 13563 (Volume 419)
  Unbound album with 78 black and white albumen photographs (most 4x5 inches, some smaller) pasted on cardboard pages. Most pages have more than one photo, some are captioned. Tourist scenes such as Stratford-on-Avon are interspersed with landscape views.
- [Butcher Shops], ca. 1910-1919; 13561 (Volume 420)
  Album of 42 silver gelatin photographs depicting the interiors of butcher shops and groceries in Brooklyn and Queens. Compiled by butcher block maker W. V. Staub.
- [World War I Victory Parade], ca. 1918-1919; 13559 (Volume 421)
  Nurses and soldiers in homecoming victory parade down 5th Avenue, 1918 or 1919.
- [Charlotte Winifred McKim], 1952-ca. 1955; 13557 (Volume 422)
  Family photograph album focusing on the first few years of Charlotte Winifred McKim's life, featuring family activities in Florida and New York, especially beach outings.
- [New York photo album], ca. 1906-1908; 13555 (Volume 423)
  Album with approximately 35 pages of black and white photographs of Central Park, Fort Washington Park, Upper Manhattan, a gypsy camp in the Bronx, and the Lower Hudson Valley.
- [Packer Collegiate Institute Portrait Album], ca. 1889; 13553 (Volume 424)
  Cabinet card album with a green velvet cover, about half the portraits are of young women from the Packer Collegiate Institute class of 1889. Other images include formal portraits of women in hats, children, and a few men.
- [Empty Cabinet Card album], 13551 (Volume 425)
  Empty cabinet card album, with red printed velvet cover, and color scene of a mill on the front.
- Hotel Normandie, 13549 (Volume 426)
  Album of six albumen interior and exterior photographs of the Hotel Normandie, New York City, Ferdinand P. Earle, proprietor.
- [Houses designed by William Edgar Moran], ca. 1901-1904; 13547 (Volume 427)
  Disbound album of gelatin silver photographs of three New York City houses, all designed by architect William Edgar Moran, of McKim, Mead & White architectural firm. The houses belonged to Thomas B. Clarke (22 East 35th Street), Payne Whitney (972 Fifth Avenue), and J.C. Lyons (973 Fifth Avenue). A few clippings and some correspondence is also included.
- [Family Cabinet Card Album], ca. 1880-1910; 13545 (Volume 428)
  Cabinet card album, with red velvet exterior and bone trim, holding late 19th and early 20th century cabinet cards, unidentified ancestors of Estelle Savage.
- [Theater Scrapbook, focusing on personalities], ca. 1890-1920; 13543 (Volume 429)
  Scrapbook filled with clippings and portraits of New York theater personalities. Inscribed "My stage crushes and favorites late '90s & early "1900s." - W.P.W." Performers include Julia Marlowe, Sarah Bernhardt, Edna May, Harry Davenport, Annie Russell, and Viola Allen.
- [Theater Scrapbook, focusing on playbills], 1911-1927; 13541 (Volume 430)
  Scrapbook filled with playbills from New York theater productions (mostly clipped from periodicals or newspapers), and related clippings and portraits of performers, or scenes from the productions. Compiled by the same person as #429.
- [Wales photo album], ca. 1890-1920; 13539 (Volume 431)
  Small photo album with stamp on inside cover from "J.E. Arnett, Bookseller, Tenby" [Wales]. Photos of castle ruins, coastal scenes with rock outcroppings and local town scenes.
- [New York City photo album], ca. 1901-1902; 13537 (Volume 432)
  Photograph album containing family snapshots, including views of New York City places and scenes. The family kept chickens and lived in a clapboard house with a porch. Possible in upper Manhattan, as other photographs show Grant's Tomb, the Soldier's and Sailor's Monument, and the beginning of construction on the cathedral Church of Saint John the Divine. Other photos show Central Park (including the zoo), the Williamsburg Bridge under construction, and boats on the Hudson River.
- [Trench and Marine Pump Co. album], ca. 1900-1940; 13535 (Volume 433)
  Album of mainly copy photography, all images show equipment manufactured by Trench and Marine Pump Co. Electric, gasoline and hand pumps are shown. Some photographs are annotated with information about how to use the pumps.
- [Upstate New York photos], 1903 June; 13533 (Volume 434)
  Unbound album with silver gelatin photographs from a trip to upstate New York. The Au Salle River, Lake Placid, Mirror Lake, Elizabethtown, and Lake George are shown.
- [New York City Landmarks Vol. 1] photographed by James J. Durna, 1976-1981; 13531 (Volume 435)
  Snapshot album with images of buildings in Manhattan and Governor's Island that had been designated landmarks by the New York City Landmarks Commission. Photographs are square Kodak color prints, the date of developing is stamped on verso. Identification of each image is written on pen on the photo's border, or else on a piece of paper included in the photo sleeve; some of these also include the dates of construction or other information about the structures. Images are arranged geographically, beginning at Governor's Island and lower Manhattan, and continuing up to Washington Heights and Inwood (at end of album.)
- [New York City Landmarks Vol. 2] photographed by James J. Durna, ca. 1975-1980; 13529 (Volume 436)
  Snapshot album with images of buildings in Brooklyn, Bronx, Queens, and Staten Island that had been designated landmarks by the New York City Landmarks Commission. Photographs are square Kodak color prints. Identification of each image is written on pen on the photo's border, or else on a piece of paper included in the photo sleeve; some of these also include the dates of construction or other information about the structures. Images are arranged by borough; some Staten Island images are loose.
- [Borden scrapbook], circa 1870's; 52967 (Volume 437)
- Souvenir Views of the commencement of excavation of the new church site for the West-Park Presbyterian Church, 174th-175th Sts. & Wadsworth Avenue, N.Y. City, 1912; 52969 (Volume 438)
- Gertrude Beach Scrapbook, 1917-1943; 52973 (Volume 439)
- The Franklin Savings Bank, 1931-1947; 52972 (Volume 440)
- Smith's Old new York, 1908, 1908-1920; 52975 (Volume 441)
- [Mead's Mountain House, Woodstock, New York], circa 1929; 52977 (Volume 442)
- Power Plants, Electrical Equipment and Machinery for Operating New York State, circa 1915; 52979 (Volume 443)
- Manus, Helaine, Photographer [Quaker Hill, New York], circa 1940; 52981 (Volume 444)
- [Album containing tintypes and cates-de-visites], circa 1860's to 1880's; 52983 (Volume 445)
- [Album of New York City postcards], circa 1930-1947; 52985 (Volume 446)
- [Photograph album of Peter Marie, his family, and his residence at 48 West 19th Street], 52835 (Volume 447)
- [Photograph album of Calvin C. Chaffee], circa 1860's; 52965 (Volume 448)
- [Photographs of 259 Tenth Avenue, architect: Cass Gilbert], 2010; 52951 (Volume 437)
- Souvenir of Southold, 1902 September; 52953 (Volume 450)
- [Tattoo sketch book], undated; 52955 (Volume 451)
- [album of lithographs of historic buildings and sites in New York City (most produced for Valentine's manual); includes Volume 8, Number 15 of "The Mentor," Literary Landmarks of New York], circa 1854-1866; 52957 (Volume 452)
- Official Portratis of our Presidents [photogravures], 1912; 52959 (Volume 453)
- [West Point album], 1866; 52961 (Volume 454)
- Photographs Union College, Schenectady NY, Class of 1866, 52963 (Volume 455)
- [Album of photographs showing construction of Rockefeller Center], 1930-1947; 52988 (Volume 456)
- [Photos and ephemera from 1939-1940 World's Fair], 53013 (Volume 457)
- Theodore D. Judah scapbook of early California lithographs (mainly Britton and Rey), 1852-1858; 54339 (Volume 458)
- [Tourist photos of New York City], 1958 August; 55320 (Volume 459)
  Snapshots of Magnolia, Ohio resident Wayne Joseph's trip to New York City. Includes landmarks, billboards, Jack Dempsey's Broadway Bar, Hudson River Day Line Tour, and interior and exterior shots of the Manhattan Hotel.
- Church of the Heavenly Rest, 90th Street and 5th Avenue, 1929; 55575 (Volume 460)
- [Scrapbook of Ladson Butler], circa 1900; 55674; Scrapbook of chromolithographs; includes Christmas and New Year's cards and images of Santa Claus, Civil War generals, royalty, children, cats, dogs and flowers. (Volume 461)
- [Photo albums; includes vacations at Mohonk Lake, picnics, croquet, and an engagement party. Also photos of WWI soldiers], 1910-1921, undated; 56512 (Volume 462.1-462.3)
- Ricordo del Campo Santo Di Genova [album of cabinet cards of Genoa sculpture], 56524 (Volume 463)
- [Album of postcards from Florida and elsewhere; includes African-American and Native American images], 56525 (Volume 464)
- [Album of post-9/11 photographs of New York], 2001 September 12-13; 56857 (Volume 465)
  Provenance
  Gift of Eleanor Surkis, 2008
  This is an album of snapshots taken by New York City resident Eleanor Surkis one or two days after 9/11, depicting businesses and homes adorned with patriotic displays.
- [Album of architectural drawings by John Trumbull], circa 1790's; 57224 (Volume 466)